Mikaela Brough

mikaela.brough.2022@live.rhul.ac.uk • Citizenship: Canadian

Profile

I am a PhD researcher in the Information Security Group at Royal Holloway, University of London. My research explores how environmental activists navigate their information security in politically risky contexts. Rather than prioritising technological solutions, I study the social first - building our understanding of security from the ground up. The ultimate aim is to understand secure systems through the lived experiences of those who explicitly rely on them. I have previously published in other areas of qualitative social research in academia and the private sector.

Current Research Interests

Social Movements, Environmentalism, Cryptography and Security Technologies, Ethnographic Methods.

Education

2022 - Present Royal Holloway, University of London - Egham, UK

PhD in Information Security

Centre for Doctoral Training in Cybersecurity

Supervisors: Dr. Rikke Jensen, Dr. Martin Albrecht

2020 – 2021 University of Oxford – Oxford, UK

MSc in Social Anthropology

Supervisor: Dr. Ina Zharkevich 1:1 Distinction.

2015 – 2019 **McGill University** – Montreal, Canada

BA in History and Art History, Minor in Political Science

GPA: 3.6.

Awards

2022 International PhD Funding with Living Stipend (Department of Information Security, Royal Holloway, University of London)

Awarded through the Engineering and Physical Sciences Research Council of UK Research and Innovation

2022 Prof David Parkin Prize in Ethnographic Materials (School of Anthropology and Museum Ethnography)

Awarded to the best use of ethnography in an MSc Dissertation

2021 Distinction (School of Anthropology and Museum Ethnography, University of Oxford)

2019 Distinction (Canadian Equivalent) (McGill University)

Publications

Father-toddler bonding during the Covid-19 lockdown: Qualitative insights from 17 families in Britain

Paula Sheppard, Mikaela Brough

Social Sciences

Fertility Decision-Making in the UK: Insights from a qualitative study among British men and women

Mikaela Brough, Paula Sheppard

Social Sciences

2021 Review of "Benno Herzog, Invisibilization of Suffering: A Moral Grammar of Disrespect"

Mikaela Brough

Journal of the Anthropological Society of Oxford

Research experience

June 2023 - **PhD Fieldwork**

present Supervisors: Dr. Rikke Bjerg Jensen, Professor Martin Albrecht

Ethnographic fieldwork in the UK and the Southern Philippines for PhD thesis. Recruitment, Data Collection (interviewing, participant observation, focus groups, workshops, etc.).

August 2021 - **Research Assistant**

January 2022 Principal Investigator: Dr. Paula Sheppard (University of Oxford)

Qualitative research project on UK fertility gap/decline. Summary of findings available here and here. Recruitment, Data Collection, Data Analysis, Writing, Editing, Publishing.

June 2018 – August 2018	Salapia Exploration Project Mentors: Dr. Darian Totten (McGill University), Dr. Roberto Goffredo (Università degli studi di Foggia)
	Relevant industry experience
2016 - 2020	Researcher (Boxing Cats Productions) - Toronto, Canada
Summer 2020	Canadian Emergency Commercial Rent Assistance Officer (First Canadian Title) – Oakville, Canada
	Talks / Conferences
March 2023 - present	Attendee (Various Events) – Real World Crypto (x2), ACM CHI
August 2024	Presenter – Talking about Information Security <i>Various (x4 venues), Cebu, Philippines.</i>
June 2024	Presenter – Information Security in Environmental Movements Inter-CDT Conference, Bristol, UK.
May 2024	Presenter – On the Virtues of Information Security in the UK Climate Movement <i>ReCAP, Re-imagining Cryptography and Privacy, Massachusetts, USA.</i>
April 2024	Presenter – On the Virtues of Information Security in the UK Climate Movement <i>CDT Showcase, Windsor, UK.</i>
June 2023	Presenter – Exploring Secure Messaging and Perceptions of Risk: A Literature Review STS Italia, Bologna, Italy.
April 2023	Presenter – Exploring Software Developers Perceptions of Security <i>CDT Showcase, Windsor, UK.</i>
April 2022	Presenter – Fertility Decision Making in the UK: Insights from a qualitative study across British social classes European Human Behaviour and Evolution Association conference at the Max Planck Institute for Evolutionary Anthropology, Leipzig, Germany.

Reviewing

September 2022 Perspectives on Sexual and Reproductive Health

Peer review

September 2023 USENIX Security Symposium

Peer review

Skills

Programming Languages

Proficient in: Python, R, Bash Familiar with: C, SQL

Technical Skills

Network security: Good knowledge of network protocols, architecture

Cryptography: Proficiency in conventional cryptographic algorithms, key management, key exchange. Basic knowledge of PQC

Operating systems: Proficiency in how to configure and manage security settings on Mac, Windows, and Linux

Scripting: Good knowledge of scripting languages (Bash, Python, Powershell)

Legal: Good knowledge of major legal and regulatory frameworks for security (e.g., GDPR)

Languages

English (fluent), Italian (advanced), French (intermediate), Tagalog (basic)

Other

 $Ethnography, participant\ observation, qual/quant\ data\ collection/analysis, interviewing$